so we have seen what a single bit in
memory looks like now let's see how the
whole chip is organized we said already
that we have these word lines that
activate cells we have a number of word
lines and the thing that decides which
word line gets activated is called a row
decoder what we give to the row decoder
is some bits of the address that tell it
which of the word lines to activate it
can only activate one word line at a
time so this is a real decoder you give
it a number it activates a line that
corresponds to that number in memory we
call this row address there is also a
bit line here and if you remember a
memory cell exists at every intersection
between this bit line and a word line so
what a word line does is it connects
this cell this cell this cell or this
cell to the bit line
so by supplying let's say two bits of
the address we choose which of the four
bits would be outputting on this one bit
line of course there are more bit lines
than just one and this for example is a
16bit memory it's a 4x4 bit memory four
bits can output to the same bit line and
there are four bits activated by each of
the word lines so when we select the row
four bits get output out of here now bit
lines are very long and as we said the
cell is either a relatively weak SRAM
cell so it will slowly pull the bit line
one way or the other or it is a dram
cell that discharges are relatively
small capacitor into this relatively
long bit line if we discharge a small
capacitor into a long bit line the
voltage on the bit line will change but
it will change relatively little it will
not change all the way to the level that
corresponds to a one or to a zero if we
have a weak cell we don't want to wait
for that cell to raise the whole bit
line one way or the other this is why
the bit lines are connected to a device
called sense amplifier what it does is
it senses the small changes on the bit
line and amplifies them so it's really
helping the cell raise or lower the
voltage on the bit line and it has
relatively powerful circuitry for each
bit line so it's significantly bigger
than a single row of cells but you only
need one of these at the end of the bit
line you don't need one of these at
every cell so you have relatively small
and weak cells and you have this beefy
thing here that is helping them raise or
lower the bit line the signals that are
produced by the sense amplifier which
are now correctly one or zero bits go to
a storage element called row buffer the
row buffer stores the correct values
that we read from the whole row of cells
so in this case the row buffer will
contain four bits because that's how
many bits are there in the row the row
buffer feeds the data it latched to
another decoder that is called the
column decoder this decoder selects the
correct bit among these four let's say
using the column address which is
another part of the data address and it
outputs a single bit if we want to build
something that has more than just one
bit of data for each location we will
replicate this so we will have let's say
two of these give them the same row and
column address and now they output a
2bit value